[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is a note on, you know, there's patīcampādā.
[SPEAKER_01]: The note in itself, it's quite long.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about 25 paragraphs.
[SPEAKER_01]: It gets very technical, so I think I'd rather speak about the principle of patīcampādā, that then people can...
[SPEAKER_01]: Dwell on, reflect, keep in mind, and then when they read Jnanavira's note on Pratītya Upāda, you can sort of give more of a context, rather than dealing with every particular point that Jnanavira himself raises in in his notes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the points are self-explanatory, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: The refutation of the traditional interpretation and so on, it's all in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I thought maybe just to contribute to the general perspective,
[SPEAKER_01]: This is based upon the principle of paticca-upādā and also practical application that can... that can then result in freedom from ownership, that then results in freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That if you're not seeing, you're with the grain of it, as the sūtra described, means ignorance is the cause for your outlook towards the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously, right there and then, if you're seeing,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you're against the grain of it, which means the principle still remains there, but it's the direction of it that has changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, his insistence on bodhisattva-padā being the one-life interpretation, it's not really an interpretation in a sense of
[SPEAKER_01]: That, eh... there can be different interpretation.
[SPEAKER_01]: His insistence was ultimate, in a sense of this is the principle that cannot be diluted or compromised.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes people say, oh yes, some other, other teachers also are teaching the Paticca Upādā is only, eh... it's a present principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you look at it, how their interpretation of it, how their view of it goes, it comes down to... it's still the commentarial type of outlook, as in, it's still taken to be an explanation, just instead of spreading it over three lifetimes, they get to... they concentrate it, and it's all in this one, or in one moment or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even momentary, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a simultaneous principle, that as such, it's timeless.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's akālika.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the principle of simultaneous presence of two different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot be examined or taken apart individually, without the other one being implied.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Patitsa Upāda and the principle of Sankhāra, it's basically the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we should probably address, but I think that has to be a separate video, the whole
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a phenomenon of saṅkhara, the determination, because most people's ideas about determinations and paticca-upādā are on the lines of a cause and effect, which is exactly what the traditional interpretation is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That this is the cause, this is the result, and this is another cause, and then another result, and so on and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, if it's a cause and effect, it must involve time.
[SPEAKER_01]: As such, it cannot be that fundamental principle that can sort of... well, make you understand the nature of action, the nature of ownership and the nature of... the nature of craving and the nature of ignorance that takes you with that grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever there is an involvement of time in the explanation or the principle,
[SPEAKER_01]: Means it is not as fundamental as Paticcan Upāda is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how every Paticcan Upāda formulation, because there are a few different ones, they will vary in the suttas, but always it will start with whenever... with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the presence of this, this is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are various translations of this as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, that both sides of that statement are in the present tense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, oh, when this has arised, having arised, ceased, then this is the result that came after it, which is usually how people take what it's own value to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, with this, this is, or with this, this comes to be, or with this, there is the being of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two things simultaneously present on two different levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's also so hard to see, because it's not something you can just observe,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it already includes your observation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nature of your observation is already implied in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like nāma, rūpa, viññāṇa, viññāṇa, nāma, rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: You look at one, it's implied by the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... so the whole point... the whole point of this... of... of discernment of this principle is because it automatically disables you, basically, from any sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you realize there is no place for a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: in the two equally, simultaneously, mutually determined things.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you look at one, it's determined by the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you look at the other, it's determined by the other one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you can't even, like the way I'm describing it, you can't even look at it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't look at the one and then look at the other, because that would require you to step outside of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's not possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... the actual... the actual principle of two simultaneous things
[SPEAKER_01]: You are within those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your experience as a whole is within those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't see them on equal footing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only see one and then discern that it's determined by the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that discernment is a valid thing, if you know how to do it, if you know where to look for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you expect to see, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: The two simultaneous things present together, to the equal extent in front of you, means you're the third thing, which means these are not the two fundamental things upon which your whole experience rests.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... the whole principle of that pathasambhāra can be summed into whenever... with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even the scholars who kind of endorse the traditional interpretation,
[SPEAKER_01]: Even they could not negate the fact that this is the very basic statement, very fundamental statement for every paticcaṁapada always implies present-present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why some of the more renowned ones tried to reconcile this, well, discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they try to reconcile it basically by dismissing it, by dismissing this most condensed formulation.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would say things like
[SPEAKER_01]: That a statement that with this, this is, is just an abstract principle of patisambhāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's quite a poor attempt, I suppose, at circumventing the problem, because no matter how abstract the principle might be for you, if it's a principle, it means that
[SPEAKER_01]: What is to follow as a description of a principle cannot be diametrically opposed to that principle, which is, again, a belief that many of the famous scholars would have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is a principle that states, with the rising of this, this is...
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, the actual explanation of principle completely ignores the very principle of simultaneous presence, and then carries on in explaining to you a three-life interpretation of how this leads to that, and then this leads to that, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if we take it to be an abstract principle, as such, everything else that follows and counter it, must be included in the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, it's not a principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that the scholars themselves call it a principle, means they understand the importance of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because that principle remains the same, that's why what Thich Nhat Hanh by the formulation found in the suttas was not always comprised of twelve factors.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are numerous occasions where, was it, saḷāyātana was omitted, then there was another occasion where it doesn't even go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Into the whole dependence of... in whole determination of saṅkhara to viññāṇa and avijja to saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it just comes to... nāmarūpa is determined by viññāṇa and viññāṇa is determined by nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or another ones in... in Digha Nikaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where, where it's, where it stops after the, what was it, after feeling and craving and then taking up the rods and fights and quarreling and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize human action is based on the principle of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what Bhaktivinoda explains you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And human action is always present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like whatever, that's why your intentions determine your, your present intentions determine your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where you're fully bound by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And being... those intentions always being present means there is always present ignorance in regard to those actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you remove the ignorance, means your actions are not determined by it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means your actions are then free from sense of self, conceit, ownership and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means there is no action of putujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no action that will perpetuate, that will maintain your... your persistence in the domain of saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the whole idea of... of the three
[SPEAKER_01]: The rebirth and so... Again, it's based on the external projection, external view of yourself, whereby there is this public world which we inhabit and then, for as long as I'm ignorant, I will be...
[SPEAKER_01]: I will travel, like, from this life to another life, to another life, to another life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what those people fail to see, there is no such public world that can be known independently from your experience, right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, when you think about a public world, you're thinking it privately, within your experience as a whole, and you're fully enclosed within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's again, that's what it means, whatever you do stays with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the idea of rebirth being like this, traveling through this public world that we all inhabit, it's completely mistaken.
[SPEAKER_01]: The idea of rebirth is closer to the persistence of your point of view that you have right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I'm not saying about persistence of your self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point of view, the direction of your view, that's what stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what always... that's why you can remember previous lives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's through this point of view, same as you remember yesterday, same as you remember ten days ago, ten years ago, if you develop your mind, some people have the ability to remember ten lifetimes ago.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, because they transcended this five aggregates, which is impossible, you still stay within it, but your view of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: reaches further back.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the only reason it can reach further back is because all it's within the same container of the five... of this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said it himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: If one person remembers one life, five lifetimes, five hundred lifetimes, all they do remember is these five aggregates or one among them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole idea of this rebirth being this traveling through this mysterious universe, and that Bhattishtha Mahārāja explained it, is completely based on this fallacy of the external world,
[SPEAKER_01]: That you can experience objectively, independent of your point of view, right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that... that's also another way... Nyanagiri doesn't necessarily talk about that, but that's... that's another take on... as to why, regarding Patitsanvara's explanation, is wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's really nothing to explain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's either the point of view,
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you go with the grain, with ignorance, with the craving, with lust and desire, or the point of view that has been purified, fully purified and and uprooted any... any... uprooted from any greed, aversion or delusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in practical terms, eh... the... the principle of paticampada, it's not about understanding
[SPEAKER_01]: The connections between the twelve factors, or sixteen factors, or eight factors, it's about seeing the principle for yourself, right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that principle is, with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is exactly the... the... the... what Sotāpanna sees when he becomes a Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, whatever has the nature of arising, has the nature to cease, because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he has a reason, that's why it will cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he doesn't need to see the cessation in order to know the impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the contrary,
[SPEAKER_01]: The impermanence, the cessation is implied in the presence of thing, presence on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever has the nature of arising, because of that nature, it will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: But usually people expect, I must see the destruction, disappearance of this thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes, that's impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, how everything got destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: They fail to see that seeing the destruction has a reason for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's a manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the impermanence that the Buddha talks about, it's on the level of that presently enduring manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever that manifestation might be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's a manifestation of something being created, or a manifestation, in your experience, of something being destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, manifestation is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's manifested, that's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's manifested on its own, that's why I can't own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what Paticca Samupādā principle is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing that the independence of the arisen phenomena, independence from your point of view, upon which your point of view must rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if this thing hasn't arisen on its own, you would not simply... well, you would not exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would not even be able to conceive it as mine, let alone appropriate it further and act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practically, you want to see the simultaneous presence of two things that determine your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing outside of it, because when you think outside, that's your internal experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't step outside of your five aggregates, and there is no need to.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is to see that five aggregates are
[SPEAKER_01]: Fully operating, fully self-sufficient, as they are, without any need of ownership or the master agent that controls them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Furthermore, once you start seeing it, you realize it's impossible to own them and it's impossible to control them, because that would require you to step outside of it and take possession of it, take the direction of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not incidental that attavāda, the self-view, one of the first factors that... first three factors that Sotāpanna abandons, it's not incidental that attavāda is... it is that assumption of the extra-temporal changeless self, self that's independent of your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like all feeling, perception, all of this, but my self is this ultimate entity that's beyond that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start to see that your sense of self, which is real as such, it's not an illusion,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's real as a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mistakes are real.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're mistaken in its content, but phenomenologically, an arising of mistake is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that mistake is human existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: That mistake is based on ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you'll know there is a mistake if there is lust in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will know there is an existential mistake if there is ill-will in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will know there is an existential mistake if there is delusion, appropriation, conceit, sense of self in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, these are the symptoms of that existential discrepancy that you are maintaining.
[SPEAKER_01]: That mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first you need to acknowledge it, because it's just saying, oh, it's not real, nothing's real, there's no self, there's nothing real there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're dismissing the entire mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're certainly not going to understand the principle of simultaneous dependence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, seeing it as a mistake, as a real, persisting mistake, is the first step.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I have a sense of self that I cannot deny.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Denying it is the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can that sense of self be there, continue existing, persist in its manifestation, without this random living operating body, beating heart, breathing lungs, without this world being persisting there, being unaffected, without the eight great elements allowing it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I remain even for a second longer if something comes and just wipes away my entire body, just gone, disintegrates?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about denying sense of self, it's about putting it in the right place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that right place is second to the experience as a whole that is first, second to the body, second to the form, feeling, perception, intentions, and second to the consciousness, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't want to be denying it, you want to change the order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, as the as the suttas would say, when somebody would understand, when they would be teaching, like, oh, it's like, like, like, eh... correcting the order, putting first that which was second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to, you want to reset the order properly, because that's the only way you can approve that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Denying it still affirms it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indulging it affirms it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignoring it maintains it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maintains its already existing affirmation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you can do, though, is see dependent on that which cannot be your sense of self, which is
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, your body, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your functioning heart, functioning brain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not saying those functions, yet your whole life depends upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's because people don't think about these things sufficiently enough, that's how you get to ignore the mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: of ownership and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start think about it, then you all gonna... then you will realize that even the most personal sense of self is still directly dependent upon the basis of this life for which you have no say in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then all you can truly say, ah, with the arising of... with the persistence of this, this persists.
[SPEAKER_01]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without this, this cannot be.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no room for me in between or outside or left or right from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There never was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing there never was room in there for you, that's how you place yourself in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another quick practical take on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Usually, people think, I am because of that things are mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Start reversing that view and start regarding it as no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because I keep taking things as mine, that's why I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you... when you have been taking things as yours for so long,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how that sense of I am starts taking priority and then taking things as mine, which is really the cause, the fuel for the sense of I am, becomes second and is seen as a result of because of I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you, again, if you deny I am, then you deny the whole problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is sense of self and you don't want to deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to regard it as not belonging to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, my own sense of self is not actually mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why it's not mine?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it depends upon... it's fully determined, its manifestation persists on account of things that I cannot own at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, my sense of self depends upon that which cannot be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, how can that sense of self belong to me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it's truly mine, its origins, its control, would be within my power.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can say this is mine, this obeys to me, until it's taken away, which means it was never really yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha compared the whole existence, the sense existence, everything, to the, like, borrowed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Borrowed jewelry, borrowed gold, sensuality, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You borrow it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you have something borrowed, you're using it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As if it's yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not necessarily a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is when you forget that you borrowed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what ignorance is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's too unpleasant to keep maintaining the perspective that this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: My feelings are not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that are dearest to me are only borrowed.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm nothing, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's quite frightening, if the mind hasn't been used to thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first protocol is ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the easiest, with-the-grain solution, is just, I'll ignore the fact that this is borrowed, that this will be taken away and I cannot own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, just because of that ignorance, this whole mass of suffering arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why Arahant, who stops ignoring that, who can never ignore it again, still speaks, talks, uses, eats, walks and so on, but he doesn't... he cannot mistake any of that for any ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: He cannot conceive it, as the sutta say, as mine, as belonging to me, as I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's important to maintain these perspectives, because it's simply through not dwelling on them, that's how you... that's how you...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you perpetuate the existential mistake I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: By ignoring it, you're fueling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not incidental that thinking about it is very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how Mara makes sure that nobody thinks about it voluntarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: Takes determination, effort and repetitive sort of strength and training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's completely against the whole nature of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: To not think about it and to go with what's offered to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I am because, or rather, the sense of me, sense of, sense of I am, or I am my own because I take things to be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the simultaneous presence of the assumed ownership is why there is a sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without that basis being there persisting, there cannot be a sense of I am persisting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you remove the basis that is necessary for your sense of self?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can't remove it as in to prevent it from arising, because that would imply that your sense of self is in control of it and has say as to what arises and what disappears, but you can stop regarding it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: How you stop regarding it as yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by stop gratuitously delighting and welcoming sense pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: I stop gratuitously trying to get rid of the unpleasant feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's desire and lust in regard to feelings, that's how you maintain the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unquestioned desire, unquestioned lust, the ownership gets maintained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unquestioned ownership, sense of self is fully established, having a grip over you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, my sense of self does not belong to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there as an arisen, persisting phenomenon, but I cannot own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if I want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Another way to think about it is, eh... understand the nature of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just take, take a phenomenon of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Belonging.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What, what does it, what is it, eh... what is it determined by?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you say, this is mine, what does that really mean to you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it mean you have a, you have a say in it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it mean you're truly the owner?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, if you start thinking about it, you realize, well, it's, it's, at most, sense of ownership is
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the level of entitlement.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be more than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just cannot be more than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you made something, you created it yourself from scratch.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that all those scratches that you had, from which you were able to create these things, they were given to you beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, it doesn't matter how far you exercise your creation, your sense of self, your ownership, your control, it's always going to be secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that persisting basis of things having arisen beforehand on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have no say in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha would encourage to think about the four great elements, which is things that arisen on their own and you have no say in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when those four great elements change, nothing that has been depending upon them can remain standing unaffected.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sense of ownership, you can reflect on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's necessary, presently, enduring basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any sense of ownership, object, people, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oi!
[SPEAKER_00]: Come here, you!
[SPEAKER_01]: Any sense of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: If something is mine, if something is truly mine, let it in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't rush answering it or defining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just, what does it mean to have things belong to me?
[SPEAKER_01]: What does it mean being mine?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you realize that, as I said, it's on the level of entitlement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you can also see that being mine means being pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: means having... implying a prospect of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you gladly regard something as mine, if that thing is threatening to you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be happy about having cancer, or a disease, or something that can kill you?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want this to be mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a common thread to everything that's regarded as mine, which is pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's not incidental, and in the video talks about it, that pleasure is... the sense of mastery over things, it's inherently bound to pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if there is no pleasure, you would not want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would certainly not be indulging the ideas of control and... and... and mastery over such things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sense of mind is a sense of entitlement that is bound
[SPEAKER_01]: With a sense of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means then, sense of mind is basically sense of entitlement towards pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You feel like you have a right to experience pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, see, to that... just to that extent only, the view has only already transgressed into domain that doesn't belong to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of the aggregated feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no right to choose what you want to feel or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yet you feel entitled.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is that entitlement rooted in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's rooted in me ignoring the fact that I have no right to choose what I feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, simply through ignoring what's right in front of you, you develop the sense of entitlement, which is a sense of ownership, which is a sense of myself, the master, the ego, everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole suffering and the mess that comes from it, comes from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: ignoring the simple truths that are right in front of you, the universal truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the presence of this, this is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with the presence of all these... with the presence of feelings, for example, my craving is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I crave for pleasure if feeling is not there in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I crave for pleasure when the feeling has disappeared?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the persistence of the arisen pleasure that's necessary, simultaneous basis for my craving of that pleasure, towards or against from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's patitsaṁpāda in the nutshell.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can I then not crave in the presence of pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly the patitsaṁpāda that goes against the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, on externally, so to speak, on the surface, nothing has changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: The aggregates remain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what has changed is the attitude of craving towards, or against, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The attitude of craving has disappeared.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, there is no craving on the basis of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the pleasure still arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the pain still arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the neutral feeling still arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the direction of... that was based on ignoring the the nature of these things that arise on their own, the five aggregates, eh... that direction is gone, because you stopped ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why ignorance, in a way, it's quite a good... good translation for avijja, because avijja is not... it's not a metaphysical secret, no... a lack of, sort of, information that... that you need to discover through some mystical practice, that will be revealed to you, some truths that are hidden.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually your very attitude towards your own feelings, your own perceptions, your own intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: The attitude of ignoring the fact that you can't own it, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you realize that you want to, only because you think you can own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you stop ignoring that... And again, you can't do that overnight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because ignoring has been done for eons and eons and eons and eons.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's been done for so long.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Buddha meant Avijja has no discernible beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before which, eh... the mind wasn't ignorant, and then it's ignorant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, avijja, as ignorance, shouldn't be there, because it's incompatible with the way things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why arahantship is irreversible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you fully realize that avijja shouldn't be there, it cannot be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It ceases to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the Buddha said, oh, that's... that's when... when his mind realized the mind was always pure and bright.
[SPEAKER_01]: The aggregates were always unpolluted by... by avijja, by craving, because it cannot be in the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not understanding the aggregates, that's why it was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you understood, that's why it can never be there ever again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Irreversible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Parinibbāna.